Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today’s דף daf is ל"ח. lamed chet.
We pick up on in the middle of ל"ז עמוד ב'. lamed
zayin amud bet. I’m sorry, I got that wrong. Today’s דף daf
is ל"ט. lamed tet. I’m sorry. Whoops. All right, today’s דף daf
is ל"ט, lamed tet, and we pick up in the middle of
ל"ח עמוד ב'. lamed chet amud bet.
So, where are we? The גמרא Gemara says like this. It’s dealing
with the cases in the משנה. Mishnah. Here, you might remember, we’ve
got a wonderful picture here. So, what happens if רחל Rachel is
a שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, and she’s got, she inherits property, which
we would normally call in American נכסי מלוג. nichsei milug. She inherited
it while she was שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. She has the title
to it. If she was married in נישואין, nisuin, then her husband
would be eating the פירות, peirot, and what the משנה Mishnah says
is, is that she has full title to it, she can buy
and sell it, no problem, even בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית
הלל Beit Hillel both agree. But, if she dies, then there’s a
debate who inherits her, whether לבן Lavan the father gets it all,
or whether they split it. So the question is, why if בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says it gets split with שמעון Shimon when she
dies, which seems to be that he has a possible like a
ספק נישואין safek nisuin type of a status there, that זיקה zika
is a ספק נישואין safek nisuin according to this idea, why does
he not get it while she’s alive? And the גמרא Gemara first
made the distinction, not about alive or dead, but about whether it
was אירוסין eirusin or נישואין, nisuin, but now the גמרא Gemara is
focusing on the idea there is a difference of alive or dead.
When she’s alive, she definitely has title, so therefore she’s a ודאי.
vadai. שמעון’s Shimon claim is only a ספק, safek, if he’s entitled
to the פירות, peirot, but she definitely has title over the land,
and אין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי ein safek motzi midei vadai even
בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees to that. When she dies, there’s a
debate who has title to the land and that’s where בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says they split it. Okay, so that’s the basic position
that בית שמאי Beit Shammai is of the opinion of אין ספק
מוציא מידי ודאי. ein safek motzi midei vadai.
He would even concede that in this case where she actually does
have undisputed title. And then the question is, but we had another
case where it seems like בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that it
doesn’t matter that somebody starts with a presumption of ownership or with
the title, we would still split it by a ספק. safek. A
case throughout the house falling on a קטן katan and his father,
and whether the creditors can claim a portion of the property. And
the גמרא Gemara says that’s because בית שמאי Beit Shammai there says
that a שטר shtar that is time to be paid, it’s like
they already have collected it. So when the question is, does it
go to the heirs or does it go to the creditors, that
nobody is more מוחזק muchzak than another according to בית שמאי. Beit
Shammai. It’s not like you say oh, it goes to the heirs
and then the question is can the creditors now exact their debt,
you know, or sort of exercise their lien. That would be a
ספק safek coming to take from the ודאי. vadai. It definitely goes
to the heirs, can the creditors now exercise their lien? But no,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai holds that שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי, shtar
ha-omed ligvot k'gavuy dami, it’s like they’ve already taken possession of it,
and therefore that’s exactly the question, who has title. Okay, so that’s
right now the two assumptions we’re making for בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
They concede that if somebody is in possession אין ספק מוציא מידי
ודאי, ein safek motzi midei vadai, and they also say that having
a שטר shtar whose time is to pay is like you’re already
in possession. Now the גמרא Gemara continues ל"ח עמוד ב' lamed chet
amud bet and it says the following: ומנא תימרא, u-minal teimra, it
is four lines down in the wide lines, about a third of
the line in. ומנא תימרא, u-minal teimra, where do I know this?
That בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, if you want to read five
lines before that, קסברי בית שמאי שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי דמי, kasbari
Beit Shammai shtar ha-omed ligvot k'gavuy dami, that if it’s time to
collect the document, it’s like they’re already in possession of it, and
therefore they are equally מוחזק. muchzak. ומנא תימרא, u-minal teimra, where do
you know this from? דתנן, de-tenan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah,
מתו בעליהן עד שלא שתו, metu ba'aleihen ad she-lo shatu, you have
women, it doesn’t matter it could be one woman, who is a
סוטה, sotah, right? She was suspected of committing adultery, she was warned,
she was seen in private. She has to now drink the סוטה
sotah waters. Now, the, now let’s say their husband died, her husband
died before they had an opportunity to drink the waters. So here’s
the question: How much is a woman in the status of a
סוטה sotah already seen as pretty much divorced from the husband until,
you know, sort of like she’s, they’re not allowed to have sex,
how much is she should have seen as already out, and that
you need the process of drinking the סוטה sotah waters to make
her acceptable again and bring her back in? Or how much is
she not yet seen as out? What’s the relevance to this question?
Well, for example, one הלכה halacha we know they can’t have sex,
but everybody agrees to that. But the relevance is, the husband dies,
they haven’t drunk the סוטה sotah waters. Can they collect the כתובה
ketubah or not? Right? So in that state of being a סוטה,
sotah, are they base, are they still entitled to a כתובה ketubah
at that stage before they’re, without the possibility of their status being
clarified. So that’s the question. If they definitely committed adultery the answer
would obviously be no. So let’s take a look. מתו בעליהן עד
שלא שתו, metu ba'aleihen ad she-lo shatu, בית שמאי אומרים נוטלות כתובתן
ואין שוטות, Beit Shammai omrim notlot ketubatan ve-ein shotot, they can collect
their כתובה, ketubah, no problem. ובית הלל אומרים או שוטות או לא
נוטלות כתובתן, u-Beit Hillel omrim o shotot o lo notlot ketubatan, either
they’re going to drink, and if they’re not going to drink the
waters they can’t get their כתובה. ketubah. So the גמרא Gemara says
what do you mean? shosos, drink the waters, והביא האיש את אשתו
אמר רחמנא וליכא. Ve-hevi ha-ish es ishto amar Rachmana ve-leika. You can't
drink the water when the husband is dead. It says the husband
has to bring his wife. אלא, Ella, you're right. So that's what
בית הלל Beis Hillel means. What בית הלל Beis Hillel means is
מתוך שלא שותות, mitoch shelo shosos, because they don't have the ability
to drink, לא נוטלות כתובתן, lo notlos kesubasan, they can't collect their
כתובה. kesubah. So בית הלל's Beis Hillel's clear. בית הלל's Beis Hillel's
basic position is once, either she fundamentally is considered already on the
outs until she can prove that she's back in, or because she's
like a ספק safek whether she has rights to the כתובה kesubah
and the heirs already have control of the estate, right? It's like
if you're coming with a debt, you're coming to take out from
the people who have the title to the estate. So that would
be a case of אין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. ein safek motzi
mi-yedei vadai. That's בית הלל. Beis Hillel. Great. But why does בית
שמאי Beis Shammai say she can collect? Okay, she's a ספק safek
whether she actually committed adultery or not. And the heirs are a
ודאי vadai that they inherit, they have the title. So why can
she come and collect? So the גמרא Gemara says והכא דספיקו, ve-hacha
de-sfeiku, it's a doubt, ספק זינתה ספק לא זינתה, safek zinasah safek
lo zinasah, maybe she committed adultery, maybe she did not. And because
she's ספק ומוציא מידי ודאי safek u-motzi mi-yedei vadai and
the doubtful right to collect the כתובה kesubah is coming to take
out of the hands of the heirs. And by the way, one
could even make a bigger point. Normally we might say that if
it's a ספק safek they split it. Here she collects the whole
כתובה. kesubah. So what's going on here? So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא שמע מינה, ella shema mina, you see, שטר העומד לגבות כגבוי
דמי, shtar ha-omed ligvos ke-gavuy dami, that they're not considered like the
heirs have title and now can she take the property out of
the hands of the heirs because of her כתובה. kesubah. If her
כתובה kesubah is really legitimate, she's the one who has title. So
it's not ספק מוציא מידי ודאי. safek motzi mi-yedei vadai. Same thing
we said before, that for בית שמאי Beis Shammai if there's a
שטר, shtar, if there's definitely a שטר, shtar, it's not like you
own it but with my שטר shtar I can take it from
your hands, that puts me as an outsider who has to prove
his case. No, if I actually have a legitimate שטר, shtar, I
have the title. And that's why you can collect the כתובה. kesubah.
Of course, for people that are following this, I don't know, it
gets a little complicated, not complicated like the previous session but anyway
you might want to say, one minute, okay, but how come by
the case of the house collapsing you had creditors, but there's a
question which order it happened, so they split
the collection of the debt between the heirs and the creditors. Here
how come the woman collects the entire collection of her כתובה? kesubah?
Right, you see there's a difference. It might very well be you
have title, but there's other people also. The heirs are claiming the
house fell in a different order, so we said split. Here the
heirs are claiming the women committed adultery, so why don't we say
split it here as well?
And yes, in this case, they both have equally, in other words,
they both have an equally definite claims, right? In other words, I
say it's a גבוי gavoy and whereas as opposed to the other
case it's a total lack of ידיעה, yediah, you don't know who.
Well,
I would go further. Well, I'd go further. First of all, in
that case nobody knows. In that case nobody knows. This case the
heirs are saying you committed adultery but they really don't know, right?
They're just saying it, but she is claiming from a position of
knowledge. Maybe she's lying but it doesn't matter she's claiming and she's
in a position to know that she didn't. That's one difference. Right,
the other difference would be that here the
כתובה kesubah
debt pre-existed. It wasn't yet ready to collect but she definitely at
an earlier state was definitely entitled to the כתובה, kesubah, whereas and
the כתובה kesubah debt pre-existed, whereas by the case by the creditors
and the order that the house fell, you don't know if they
ever started with any position of entitlement. So there are those differences.
Okay. So you have to work it out in each case. But
basically what we're saying is that while בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
אין ספק מוציא מידי ודאי, ein safek motzi mi-yedei vadai, and if
the person who's entitled, who has a definite claim, doesn't have to
give it up even part of it, doesn't even have to give
part of it up to somebody who's coming with a doubtful claim
from the outside. Nevertheless, if the person is coming with a שטר
shtar and it's the time to pay the שטר, shtar, then they're
both making equal claims. It's not like one has more of a
title than the other. And in sometimes you split it and in
sometimes like this case of the כתובה kesubah they might even get
it completely because of the specifics of the case. All right, so
that's the basic issue with בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. ואביי, Ve-Abaye, and ואביי,
Ve-Abaye, לאו מהא, lav me-ha, why didn't אביי Abaye who challenged רבה,
Rabba, right? רבה Rabba was the one who made this whole position
about explaining whether it's ספק מוציא מידי ודאי safek motzi mi-yedei vadai
and so on, and he asked him the case of the house
falling down
where it sounds like ספק safek is מוציא מידי ודאי. motzi mi-yedei
vadai. Why didn't he ask from this case about the כתובה? kesubah?
Better since we're talking in cases of women and נשים nashim and
so on, why'd they have to run to the case of the
house falling down? Ask from this case of כתובה kesubah where you
also see that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says a ספק safek can
be מוציא מידי ודאי. motzi mi-yedei vadai. And you would have had
to have the same answer about that the שטר shtar makes it
different. So why did he ask the case from the house? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא כתובת אשה שאני. dilma kesuvas isha
shani. No, you can't necessarily prove it just because we give strength
to the כתובה Kesuvah that that's a general rule. Why? Because כתובת
אשה Kesuvas Isha might be different, משום חינא, mishum china, because of
חן, chein, because of like attraction or charm, which means that the
Rabbis sometimes gave special special rights or special power to to the
כתובה Kesuvah that a normal creditor wouldn't have because to encourage women
to marry husbands. So, you know, so they wanted to you might
so to say they wanted to protect the woman's interests more, חן
chein is sort of saying they wanted to make it more attractive
for women to get married, maybe the husband didn't always wasn't always
a big provider, so they needed to do certain things. It's interesting
to sort of think about sort of the socio-economic realities, but that
they needed to strengthen the woman's rights in the כתובה Kesuvah in
order to again you could say to protect her interests but also
to make her more willing to commit to the marriage knowing that
her interests were more protected.
This is the suspect סוטה sotah though in
this particular okay, but nevertheless, she's entitled to the rights. We don't
start changing it just because, you know, anyway. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara said. So we didn't want to ask we didn't want
to jump to the case of סוטה sotah that you see that
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says a ספק safek can be מוציא מידי
ודאי. motzi mi-dei vaday. Maybe there are special rights because it's a
כתובה. Kesuvah. Okay, and that's why he asked by the case of
the house falling down. And again the answer was that a שטר
shtar is different, that בית שמאי Beis Shammai gives special power not
just to a כתובה, Kesuvah, but special power to a שטר. shtar.
Yes.
She drinks the סוטה sotah water so she's proving not to have
committed adultery. Yes.
Is the קידושין kiddushin back? No.
But nevertheless, women women can lose their כתובה Kesuvah rights before their
divorce. If a woman commits adultery, right, she could be stripped of
her כתובה Kesuvah rights before she's divorced.
Right, I was just responding to the thought that being accused already
is a quasi-divorce status.
Yeah, yeah I mean I was just sort of saying that in
very general terms. Okay, okay, yes. All right. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like
this. Now, ולא סיפא כתובה דמתניתין. velo seifa kesuvah demasnisin. So, okay
now we've got that another question which is that the משנה mishna
says once רחל Rachel dies, right, you might remember, what does בית
שמאי Beis Shammai say? Split it because then nobody has yet a
claim to title on this. But the משנה mishna also suggests, it
says מה יעשה בכתובתה ובנכסים הנכנסים והיוצאים עמה. ma ya'aseh biksuvasah u-venekhasim
ha-nikhnasim ve-ha-yotzim immah.
We've been focusing on this: נכסים הנכנסים והיוצאים עמה, nekhasim ha-nikhnasim ve-ha-yotzim
immah, the property that she takes. But what about the כתובה? Kesuvah?
The 200 זוז zuz that she has originally against ראובן, Reuven, now
she's trying to collect it from שמעון. Shimon. So בית הלל Beis
Hillel says, okay, you can't prove that you have a נישואין nisu'in
status vis-a-vis שמעון. Shimon. So and and she predeceased שמעון, Shimon, right?
So if she dies first, she doesn't collect her כתובה, Kesuvah, right?
If a woman dies first she doesn't collect her I mean the
heirs don't collect her כתובה, Kesuvah, right? So the only person she
might have a be able to collect כתובה Kesuvah against was ראובן
Reuven because ראובן Reuven died and then she sort of like, you
know, entitled. But if but if so she was sort of entitled
to collect her כתובה Kesuvah from ראובן Reuven because ראובן Reuven died.
But because she's שומרת יבם shomeres yavam to שמעון, Shimon, that's that
sort of might transfer to שמעון Shimon and therefore because שמעון Shimon
sort of takes over ראובן's Reuven status. So then she's not really
entitled yet to collect her כתובה Kesuvah because she's quasi-married to שמעון.
Shimon. So she's not yet sort of, you know, separated from her
husband and therefore allowed to collect her כתובה. Kesuvah. And then she
dies. So she's died now, so she died before her husband, before
the ראובן-שמעון combined husband has died. So so therefore she wouldn't be
allowed. On the other hand, maybe this isn't considered to be meaningful
and she is entitled to collect her כתובה. Kesuvah. So what do
you do with the כתובה? Kesuvah? So בית הלל Beis Hillel says
the כתובה Kesuvah in the end you're trying to collect it, whichever
claim you're making, she's trying to collect from שמעון's Shimon estate because
שמעון Shimon remember took over ראובן's Reuven estate. So שמעון Shimon is
מוחזק, muchzak, he's in possession, her claim is a ספק, safek, so
she doesn't get the כתובה. Kesuvah. Okay, so בית הלל Beis Hillel
says father gets the land because that was definitely in her possession.
כתובה, Kesuvah, where you're coming to collect from שמעון's Shimon estate, she
doesn't get. בית שמאי Beis Shammai says split it. So we understand
split the land, right? Whether it is is it is it her
title is she the one that has title to it or שמעון
Shimon the one that now is לבן Lavan the one that can
claim title or שמעון Shimon the one that can claim title, you
split the land. Okay. But why does בית שמאי Beis Shammai but
בית שמאי Beis Shammai also seems to say you split the כתובה.
Kesuvah. You let, you know, לבן Lavan on her behalf collect half
of the כתובה Kesuvah from שמעון. Shimon But why is that? שמעון
Shimon. is clearly in possession of the property, right? So why would
he say ספק מוציא מידי ודאי safek motzi mi-dei vaday in that
case? Why would that work? Okay, so why don't you see there
that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says ספק מוציא מידי ודאי safek motzi
mi-dei vaday and you're saying that he does not say it? So
the גמרא Gemara says, right, so what's the גמרא Gemara says? ולא
סיפא כתובה דמתניתין velo seifa kesuvah demasnisin לא פליג. lo palig.
No, בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't disagree in the case of the
כתובה. Kesuvah. בית שמאי Beis Shammai would say that שמעון Shimon stays
in possession of the 200 זוז, zuz, none of it
goes. Right, no, but then she had the זיקה, Zika, so it's
not
clearly yet עומד לגבות. Omed Ligvot. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
does that happen simultaneously? She has the זיקה Zika and then שמעון,
Shimon you know, comes in.
Exactly.
שמעון Shimon, takes over the relationship with ראובן. Reuven ולאו בדתני, Ve-lav
Be-Detani, is that not true? But it says that בית שמאי Beit
Shammai disagrees by the כתובה. Ketubah. מתה, Meita, she dies. מה יעשה
בכתובתה ובנכסים הנכנסים והיוצאים עמה? Mah Ya'aseh Be-Ketubatah U-Va-Nechasim Ha-Nichnasim Ve-Ha-Yotzim Imah?
בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו יורשי הבעל עם יורשי האב, Beit Shammai Omrim
Yachloku Yorshei Ha-Ba'al Im Yorshei Ha-Av, you split it all. ובית הלל
אומרים נכסים בחזקתם, U-Veit Hillel Omrim Nechasim Be-Chezkatan, that the title to
the land stays with רחל's Rachel family and the כתובה Ketubah money
stays with שמעון. Shimon So anyway, בית הלל Beit Hillel says you
go by חזקה, Chazakah, but בית שמאי Beit Shammai seems to say
split it down the middle for everything. So we understand why split
it down the middle for the property, because nobody has a primary
claim to רחל. Rachel. When she was alive, there was no question
that רחל Rachel had the title. The only question was who got
the פירות. Peirot. But now that רחל Rachel is dead, there is
a question who has the title, לבן Lavan or שמעון, Shimon. so
you split it. Nobody has more of a claim to that property
than somebody else. At least that's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai would
say. בית הלל Beit Hillel would say no, by default if רחל
Rachel had the title, it's still sort of seen under לבן. Lavan.
But you can understand בית שמאי Beit Shammai saying now that רחל's
Rachel out of the picture, they're each equally debating it. But by
the כתובה, Ketubah, right, if בית שמאי Beit Shammai says hold onto
the חזקה, Chazakah, why do they split the money that's in שמעון's
Shimon, possession that לבן Lavan is now claiming for the כתובה? Ketubah?
And the answer is בית שמאי Beit Shammai doesn't disagree. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says he does keep it. Is that true? The משנה
Mishnah says that you split it. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
הכי קאמר, Hachi Ka'amar, here's what it's saying. מתה, Meita, if she
dies, מה יעשה בכתובתה, Mah Ya'aseh Be-Ketubatah, what should you do with
her כתובה? Ketubah? Question mark. No answer. ושבקה, Ve-Shavkah, and we're now
not answering that question. Then we put a big period in the
middle of that sentence. Then we say נכסים הנכנסים והיוצאים עמה. Nechasim
Ha-Nichnasim Ve-Ha-Yotzim Imah.
Now, as far as the property is concerned, בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו
יורשי הבעל עם יורשי האב, Beit Shammai Omrim Yachloku Yorshei Ha-Ba'al Im
Yorshei Ha-Av, ובית הלל אומרים נכסים בחזקתם. U-Veit Hillel Omrim Nechasim Be-Chezkatan.
Okay,
so that's a very obviously hard read of that משנה. Mishnah. What
should you do with her כתובה? Ketubah? I don't know, but let's
talk about her property, okay? So basically claiming that בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is not saying split the כתובה, Ketubah, בית שמאי Beit Shammai
saying keep it in the possession of שמעון. Shimon אמר רב אשי,
Amar Rav Ashi, so that's obviously a hard read, but now we're
going to try to give it some support. מתניתין נמי דיקא, Matnitin
Nami Deika, this also could actually be inferred from the language of
the משנה, Mishnah, because the משנה Mishnah says יחלוקו יורשי הבעל עם
יורשי האב. Yachloku Yorshei Ha-Ba'al Im Yorshei Ha-Av.
The heirs of the husband can come and divide, meaning שמעון Shimon.
can divide it with יורשי האב, Yorshei Ha-Av, with the, you know,
like לבן, Lavan, okay? So שמעון Shimon can divide it with לבן.
Lavan. Now if you say שמעון Shimon is entitled to, שמעון Shimon
can divide it with לבן, Lavan, who sounds like the one that
is more fundamentally in possession?
שמעון Shimon because he divides with somebody else.
No, but if you say, Michael, you can divide that cake over
there with Charlie, right? I guess you're saying yeah, but עם, Im,
okay. I guess it depends. Yeah, I guess I guess it could
go both ways. But the גמרא's Gemara assuming what it means is
you're entitled to come, even though Charlie has the cake, you're entitled
to come and take your portion. So יחלוקו יורשי, Yachloku Yorshei, so
the language is יחלוקו יורשי הבעל עם יורשי האב Yachloku Yorshei Ha-Ba'al
Im Yorshei Ha-Av means the father's family has basically in possession, but
the husband's family is allowed to come and take their portion. So
that's talking about this. These are the ones which we understand is
more sort of in possession of the father's family, but שמעון's Shimon
also allowed to come and take his half, okay? So that shows
that we're talking about the נכסי מלוג. Nichsei Melog. ולאו תני, Ve-lav
Tani, if we were talking about the כתובה, Ketubah, it would have
been written in the reverse. יורשי האב Yorshei Ha-Av can come, לבן
Lavan can come and take his portion עם יורשי הבעל Im Yorshei
Ha-Ba'al from שמעון's Shimon estate. Okay, the funny thing is though if
we're talking about both, you have to take one of them to
say. So anyway, while the משנה Mishnah seems to say בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says you split both, the current claim is they concede
the case of the כתובה. Ketubah. שמע מינה. Shema Minah. Okay, so
do people get that? The read now of רבא Rava is what's
רבא's Rava read of the משנה? Mishnah? Just to remind ourselves, okay?
The read is when רחל's Rachel alive, she definitely has title. The
only question is who gets the פירות. Peirot. So therefore everybody says
that since she's definitely in possession of the title, she gets it.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai agrees to בית הלל. Beit Hillel. When she
dies, בית הלל's Beit Hillel position is hold on, whoever has the
default of possession gets it, the other person's out in the cold.
So the title of this estate had been under רחל, Rachel, so
its default sort of possession is with רחל's Rachel family. שמעון Shimon
who wants to have a ספק Safek claim, nothing. When it comes
to the כתובה, Ketubah, that's extracting money of a debt, that's a
default was in שמעון's Shimon possession, so שמעון Shimon holds onto it.
That's what בית הלל Beit Hillel says, makes sense. בית שמאי Beit
Shammai says split it. If there's a question, then according
to רבא Rava actually בית שמאי Beit Shammai does say sometimes you
stay the person in possession holds
onto. How about the case of, how about the case of the
כתובה? ketubah? So there שמעון Shimon really is in possession. Why does
he say split it? And the answer is he doesn't say split
it. Okay, we reread the משנה. mishnah. All right, so that's that's
the read that the reason בית שמאי Beit Shammai concedes this case
when רחל's Rachel alive is because then רחל Rachel is fully in
possession. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai concedes when somebody is fully in
possession, the other person is out in the cold. And therefore in
parallel we're saying that בית שמאי Beit Shammai concedes that שמעון Shimon
holds on to the full כתובה ketubah money. All right, now the
גמרא Gemara continues. That's רבא's Rava read. Now we're going to have
a few more reads about this about how to explain why בית
שמאי Beit Shammai makes concedes the first case of the משנה. mishnah.
אביי אמר, Abaye amar, רישא דנפלו כשהיא שומרת יבם, reisha denafalu keshehi
shomeret yavam, סיפא דנפלו כשהיא תחתיו דבעל. seifa denafalu keshehi tachtav deba'al.
So in the first case he says it depends when she got
the estate.
Okay,
it's not about רחל Rachel being dead. That's what רבא Rava emphasized
that when she dies the question of the title changes. That's not
what it's about. Although the משנה mishnah in the משנה mishnah that's
really only the difference between the first case and the and the
second case. So רבא's Rava read is unquestionably the פשט pshat of
the משנה, mishnah, but now we're going to say like we said
before maybe there's some other factor going on that's not being stated.
What's the other factor? When did she get this property? So let's
ask ourselves that question. If she got the property when she was
married to ראובן. Reuven. Okay, here she is, ראובן Reuven. is still
alive, hasn't died yet, and she got this property. Okay, she got
an inheritance. Who has okay, she maybe has technical title over it
but ראובן Reuven is definitely her husband and definitely has the right
to the פירות. peirot. And as we've seen before, right to the
פירות, peirot, especially in this case of נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, gives
a husband a quasi title. So ראובן Reuven has a pretty strong
claimant to you know claimant to that property when she inherits it.
Now ראובן Reuven dies. שמעון Shimon steps in into ראובן's Reuven place.
So the same way ראובן Reuven here, right, had, you know, if
you want to say רחל Rachel had the technical title and ראובן
Reuven had the title and ראובן Reuven here had the title about
the פירות, peirot, but that's also a quasi title, right, כקנין הגוף
kekinyan haguf etc. Okay. Okay,
so that's what happened when she got the property when ראובן Reuven
was alive. Then ראובן Reuven died. Well guess what? שמעון Shimon now
takes ראובן's Reuven place. Okay, or at least he somewhat takes שמעון's
Shimon place because he's got זיקה. zikah. Okay?
So now he's got a pretty good claim here because he's replacing
the property which actually ראובן Reuven had a real position in. And
שמעון Shimon is now replacing ראובן. Reuven So שמעון Shimon also will
have some real serious position in this property. Okay, and that's why
he'll be entitled to say יחלוקו yachloku when רחל Rachel dies, because
his position is a serious one. When is the period where we
say that רחל Rachel has full possession? When רחל Rachel gets it
not when ראובן Reuven. is alive but when רחל Rachel gets it
after ראובן Reuven has died. In this case she's not really married
to anyone. There's only a זיקה zikah to שמעון. Shimon So in
this case because she has the title and the relationship to שמעון
Shimon. is only quasi, right, she really establishes herself as the total
owner. Okay, and therefore she's free to do what she wants. But
in this case she never established herself as the total owner because
while she technically had title, ראובן Reuven had a real position in
the property. And therefore since she never fully established herself as owner,
even when ראובן Reuven dies and שמעון Shimon only quasi takes his
place, he also has a real position as opposed to here when
she got it after ראובן Reuven had died, so there was no
real husband, so she was clearly and undisputedly the full owner of
the property.
Yes. Aren't we saying about the כתובה ketubah that after her husband
dies then שמעון Shimon does have a
זיקה zikah have a connection to the כתובה, ketubah, but not to
the property?
No, so I don't want to talk about כתובה ketubah right now
but for the property yes he does have a position. But here
right here
in this case רחל Rachel and ראובן, Reuven ראובן's Reuven, the real
husband. So in this case in the property with a real husband,
the wife and the husband are... actually the גמרא's Gemara going to
use this phrase in a minute... pretty much coequal. Okay.
And therefore her position she never really was the full person who
had fully had title to the property. Her title was always compromised
because of the husband. So even when שמעון Shimon steps in and
even though it's a little bit weaker, she still is not really
cannot really claim like this is all mine. Okay, so they split
it. Now actually I'm simplifying it a little the גמרא's Gemara going
to tweak it. The גמרא's Gemara actually I might as well jump
to what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. The גמרא's Gemara going
to say actually in this scenario, the husband's position was actually the
stronger position. The husband was actually seen as the senior property partner
in the property. And therefore when he leaves, even though שמעון Shimon
takes his place and שמעון Shimon is a little bit is weaker,
so it goes from being a senior position to a co-equal position
and they split it. Whereas in this case, right, it never started
with a real husband. Her rights in the property were undisputed, were
not compromised. So even though שמעון Shimon is like a quasi-husband, he's
coming without her position ever having been prior been compromised beforehand and
therefore she's considered the total owner. Yes.
One thing I don't understand is I thought that שמעון Shimon does
have the possession of ראובן's Reuven property.
Yeah but this isn't ראובן's Reuven property, this is רחל Rachel is
the technical title owner of this property. ראובן Reuven only has the
right to the פירות. peros. We're not talking about the כתובה. kesuva.
We're not talking about the נכסי מלוג. nichsei milug. Even the property?
No, she owns that property.
She owns there's no question she owns the title. The question is
the husband owns the פירות peros and what position does that place
him in in the property.
We're only talking about real estate, correct?
Yes.
Not only. No no I no that's not necessarily true, that's classically
we're talking about that but that's not necessarily true. Like moveable property?
Exactly. Exactly. Okay so אביי אמר Abaye amar רישא דנפלה כשהיא שומרת
יבם reisha denafela keshehi shomeres yabam and therefore she got it, there
was no real husband in the picture, she's the undisputed title owner
and therefore she can go ahead and has full control over it.
סיפא Seifa where we say יחלוקו yachloku is not because she died
really but it's a completely different scenario, not mentioned in the משנה,
mishnah, דנפלה כשהיא תחת הבעל. denafela keshehi tachas habaal. She had gotten
it when she was still married to ראובן Reuven and therefore her
position had been compromised from the beginning and therefore she is not
a full title owner even when ראובן Reuven died. וקסבר אביי Vekasavar
Abaye and אביי Abaye holds ידו כידה yado kiyada so basically
that the husband has an equal position to that of the wife
and therefore wait
a minute
oh that's according to playing בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So what we've
now done is we've explained בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, right? We've explained
בית שמאי Beis Shammai why in this case after you know because
ראובן Reuven had the strong position here, even after he dies שמעון
Shimon becomes is an sort of an equal title holder, right? That's
what we explained why בית שמאי Beis Shammai says יחלוקו. yachloku. But
בית הלל Beis Hillel still says she keeps the whole property and
לבן Lavan gets the property. Why does לבן Lavan get the property?
Doesn't בית הלל Beis Hillel agree to this, that the ראובן Reuven
had a strong position and therefore שמעון Shimon takes over that position?
So the answer is no בית הלל Beis Hillel doesn't agree to
that. בית הלל Beis Hillel says that when ראובן Reuven was alive
they were co-equal and therefore after ראובן Reuven died, שמעון Shimon was
a lesser partner and therefore רחל Rachel became the title owner. So
the debate of בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
is when she's married to a husband is her husband's position in
the property stronger than hers? So when the husband dies and שמעון
Shimon comes in the picture they're equal then they'll split it, that's
what בית שמאי Beis Shammai says. Or is her husband's property in
the position equal to her so when her husband dies and שמעון
Shimon comes in at a lower level, she's still considered to be
the one who really has title and that's בית הלל's Beis Hillel
position. And that's why בית הלל Beis Hillel says she keeps it
and it goes to לבן. Lavan. So that's וקסבר אביי ידו כידה
vekasavar Abaye yado kiyada husband and wife are equal meaning that would
be בית הלל's Beis Hillel position. That's why בית הלל Beis Hillel
does not say split it, but that it stays in her property
because now when שמעון Shimon comes in, he comes in at a
lower level. אמר ליה רבא Amar lei Rava so now רבא Rava
said אי דנפלה כשהיא תחת הבעל, i denafela keshehi tachas habaal, no,
he
now רבא's Rava going to work completely with אביי's Abaye framework except
just disagree
with how we פוסקין pasken in the various situations. If she got
it when she was married to ראובן, Reuven דכולי עלמא לא פליגי
דידו עדיפא מידה dechulei ama lo pligi deyado adifa miyada opposite what
we just said. Everybody would say the husband's position when they're married
is stronger than the wife's position and therefore after ראובן Reuven, died
שמעון Shimon would be equal and even בית הלל Beis Hillel would
say יחלוקו. yachloku.
Because the rabbis strengthened the husband's position. We'll find about that later
in יבמות Yevamos and כתובות Kesuvas etc. but we're not going to
worry about it now. He generally has a קניין פירות kinyan peros
which is כקניין הגוף kekinyan haguf according to at least to ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish and we the חז"ל Chazal might have might have
strengthened his position even more than that. It could be, yes. So
so רבא Rava says I agree with your basic structure, I just
disagree with your פסק. psak. I hold that normal husband and wife
case the husband's position in the property is stronger. So if we
were talking about שומרת יבם, shomeres yabam, if we were talking about
she got it when she was married, everybody would agree that ראובן
Reuven was stronger and after ראובן Reuven died, שמעון Shimon becomes equal
and even בית הלל Beis Hillel would say יחלוקו. yachloku. So therefore
if that's true, so what's going on here? What's the what's the
difference, when does בית שמאי Beis Shammai concede, when does he not
concede? Says the גמרא Gemara רישא דלא עבד בה מאמר סיפא דעבד
בה מאמר. reisha delo avad ba maamar seifa deavad ba maamar. Here's
the difference. Remember that בית שמאי Beis Shammai holds that when you
do מאמר maamar with the זיקה zika introducing yet another factor not
in the משנה, mishnah, it really makes you
If this were the scenario, then even בית הלל Beis Hillel would
say יחלוקו. yachloku. So this can't be the scenario. Forget about that.
It has to be like we always thought. This was the scenario.
If this is the scenario, that she got it after ראובן Reuven
had died, so clearly she has undisputed title. If that's the scenario,
why does בית שמאי Beis Shammai say יחלוקו yachloku in this case?
Right? That's what we've been asking. Why is בית שמאי Beis Shammai
going to say יחלוקו? yachloku? And the answer is, even though she
has undisputed title, you know why בית שמאי Beis Shammai in the
סיפא seifa is going to say יחלוקו? yachloku? Because the סיפא, seifa,
it's not that she died like we said before, that's not significant.
The סיפא seifa is that on top of the זיקה zika was
added מאמר. ma'amar. And since he did מאמר ma'amar to her and
then she died, since he did מאמר ma'amar and then she died,
right, so therefore what? So therefore, he basically really became like her
husband. And once he really became like her husband and then she
died, then he gets, then, now, if it was really, there'd be
no question, he would keep it 100% because a husband, right, inherits
his wife. Even בית שמאי Beis Shammai though says יחלוקו. yachloku. So
מאמר ma'amar makes it, as we'll see, enough נשואה, n'su'ah, to a
quasi-state, that, right, that now she splits it, you know, now they're
equal and now it gets split. So let's take a look at
that.
Right. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
So סיפא דעביד בה מאמר, seifa d'avid beh ma'amar, and that's why
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says they split it. Okay. וכסבר רבא, v'chasvar
Rava, מאמר לבית שמאי, ma'amar l'Beis Shammai, מאמר ma'amar for בית שמאי
Beis Shammai
עושה ודאי ארוסה, oseh vaday arusah, makes her like as if she's
definitely ארוסה, arusah, because you remember before the whole issue of מאמר
ma'amar was about the relatives, right? And about אחות אשה achos isha
and all that fun stuff we had before. Now probably people are
saying, oh, I remember those good old days where all we were
doing was talking about אחות אשה. achos isha. Anyway, so, so, so
for מאמר ma'amar had a relevance there to define who is an
ערווה erva and a צרת ערווה. tzaras erva. But to define that,
you only have to be קידושין, kidushin, you don't need נישואין, nisu'in,
right? So now we're tweaking what we had said before and that
מאמר ma'amar for בית שמאי Beis Shammai makes her like she's married.
It makes her like there was קידושין, kidushin, which has all the
implications for ערווה erva and צרת ערווה. tzaras erva. Does it make
her like נישואין nisu'in relating to property issues? That only halfway. Okay.
So מאמר לבית שמאי עושה ודאי ארוסה, ma'amar l'Beis Shammai oseh vaday
arusah, makes her a definite ארוסה, arusah, וספק נשואה, v'safek nisu'ah, and
a questionable
נשואה. nisu'ah. ודאי ארוסה לדחות בצרות, vaday arusah lidchos b'tzaros, a definite
ארוסה arusah so the צרות tzaros gets pushed off, you know, you'll
remember vaguely those cases, but about defining who the ערווה erva is
and so on. וספק נשואה לחלוק בנכסים, v'safek nisu'ah lachlok b'nechasim, that
at least he gets half of the נכסים. nechasim. Okay. So that's
what it, so basically, we're all talking about this case. She got
it after ראובן Reuven died, רחל Rachel has the title, בית שמאי
Beis Shammai concedes רחל Rachel has the undisputed title, and therefore that's
the רישא reisha of the משנה. Mishna. Why in the סיפא seifa
do they say, does בית שמאי Beis Shammai say split it? Because
the סיפא, seifa, there was also מאמר ma'amar done, and that puts
שמעון Shimon in a quasi-נשואה n'su'ah status, which therefore leads to the
idea of splitting it.
Right. So let's take a look. איתמר משמיה דרבי אלעזר כוותיה דרבא.
Itmar mishmei d'Rabbi Elazar kvasei d'Rava. We taught in the name of
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, sort of, the אמורא Amora followed רבא's Rava
position.
ואיתמר משמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא כוותיה דאביי. V'itmar mishmei d'Rabbi Yose
b'rabbi Chanina kvasei d'Abaye. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Chanina
followed אביי's Abaye position. Okay. ומי אמר רבי אלעזר הכי? Umi amar
Rabbi Elazar hachi? Did רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar really say like
רבא? Rava? והאמר רבי אלעזר, V'ha'amar Rabbi Elazar, מאמר לבית שמאי אינו
קונה אלא לדחות בצרה בלבד, ma'amar l'Beis Shammai eino koneh ela lidchos
b'tzarah bilvad, that מאמר ma'amar for בית שמאי Beis Shammai only has
an implication for the whole ערווה erva and צרה tzarah issues, presumably
saying not for property issues at all, and רבא Rava has, so
how could he say like רבא? Rava? רבא Rava said that מאמר
ma'amar for בית שמאי Beis Shammai makes her a ספק נשואה, safek
nisu'ah, has implications for property issues. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
איפוך, eipech, fine, we got it wrong, reverse it. Okay, רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar says like אביי, Abaye, not like רבא. Rava. ואיבעית אימא
לעולם לא תיפוך, V'iba'is eima le'olam lo teipech, or you could say
don't reverse it. אמר לך רבי אלעזר, Amar lach Rabbi Elazar, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar will tell to you, say to you, כי אמרי
אנא דלא סגי לה בגט אלא דבעיא נמי חליצה, ki amri ana
d'lo sagi lah b'get ela d'ba'ya nami chalitza, when I say מאמר
ma'amar for בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't make her, only has an
implication for an ערווה, erva, I did not mean it doesn't have
implications for money issues. It does have implications for money issues. I
hold like רבא. Rava. It makes her a ספק נשואה. safek nisu'ah.
So what was the point of saying that it only pushes away
the צרה? tzarah? In what way is מאמר ma'amar not good enough?
So to say that a גט get is not sufficient, אלא דבעיא
נמי חליצה, ela d'ba'ya nami chalitza, right, that's the big חידוש chiddush
of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. You've done מאמר, ma'amar, and now would
we say that if you want to change your mind, you don't
have to do חליצה? chalitza? Right, you never did יבום. yibum. I
mean, you know, so would we actually say a גט get is
enough, you don't have to worry about חליצה? chalitza? So this is
what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is saying. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is
saying מאמר ma'amar makes her, basically what he's saying is, מאמר ma'amar
can make her an ארוסה arusah or. נשואה nesua without making her
a non-יבמה. yevama.
You understand the idea? Like it can add a level without replacing
the other state. If you do, right? So therefore, yes, you did
מאמר. ma'amar. So it's an act of קידושין. kiddushin. So you're considered
like an ארוסה, arusa, maybe you're a quasi-נשואה, nesua, maybe even for
monetary issues. Now you want to change your mind? Can you just
give a גט? get? No, because whatever you added with מאמר, ma'amar,
you didn't remove her status also as a שומרת יבם. shomeret yabam.
And if you want to now separate it, you need not only
a גט get but also חליצה. chalitza. Okay, so that's what he's
saying. I didn't mean to say you don't have property rights. She's
a quasi-נשואה nesua as well. What I meant was you haven't completely
replaced her יבמה yevama status and if you want to get a
divorce now you also need חליצה. chalitza.
I don't understand how a גט get would take care of... like
I understand...
Let me just see the next five words. Okay. אלא דבעי נמי
חליצה. Ella d'ba'ei nami chalitza. לחלוק בנכסים דלא קני מימי. Lachlok b'nichasim
d'lo kani miamai. I never said that the husband doesn't get a
portion of the property. מאמר ma'amar will work to make her an
ארוסה, arusa, maybe to make her a quasi-נשואה, nesua, all that is
fine, but since it's not yet יבום, yibum, if you want to
separate, there's still a יבמה yevama status and חליצה chalitza will still
be needed. Okay, what's your question?
No, it just... I just have the wrong concept of a גט.
get. In other words, I...
No you don't, it's just that we're saying that you added a
status, you did not remove the old one. Good, you did a
קידושין. kiddushin. Good, she's מקודשת. mekudeshet. Maybe she's even a נשואה. nesua.
Fine, but she's still also a יבמה yevama that needs either חליצה
chalitza or יבום. yibum. You didn't do חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum.
So she's both.
All right.
אמר רב פפא: Amar Rapa: סיועא דמתניתין כוותיה דאביי, Siyu'ka d'matnitin k'vatei
d'Abaye, the read of our משנה Mishna supports אביי. Abaye. ואף על
גב דקשיא מתה, Ve'af al gav d'kasha meisa, even though the case
of dying is difficult in this case of the משנה. Mishna. דתני,
De-tani, the משנה Mishna says: נכסים הנכנסים והיוצאים עמה. Nichasim hanichnasim ve-yotzin
imah. When it speaks about the property she inherits, it describes it
as the property that comes in and goes out with her. מאי
נכנסים ומאי יוצאים? Mai nichnasim ve-mai yotzin? What does it mean coming
in and going out? That's a funny phrase. לאו, Lav, it must
mean נכנסים לרשות הבעל ויוצאים מרשות הבעל לרשות האב. nichnasim l'reshut habaal
ve-yotzin mirshut habaal l'reshut ha'av. Where's she taking this property? Property that's
coming in and going out with her. What is it, Mary's little
lamb? Where's she taking this property? So it says where she's taking
it is, this proves אביי. Abaye. Because we're talking about in the
second case of יחלוקו, yachloku, אביי Abaye said why is it יחלוקו?
yachloku? Because she got the property when she was married to ראובן.
Reuven So it came into her, she inherited it when she was
married to ראובן, Reuven. נכנסים, nichnasim, and it was יוצאים עמה, yotzin
imah, it left with her when ראובן Reuven, died. So that's what
it means נכנסים והיוצאים עמה. nichnasim ve-yotzin imah. That's the way to
describe the property she inherited when she was under ראובן. Reuven So
that phrase shows us that the second case of the משנה Mishna
is talking about property she got while she was married to ראובן.
Reuven. I, we were saying, oh it's not in the משנה, Mishna,
how can you introduce this new factor? He says no, the phrase
נכנסים והיוצאים עמה nichnasim ve-yotzin imah is only used in the end
of the משנה. Mishna. And that shows you we're talking specifically about
property she got while she was married to ראובן. Reuven. Okay, that's
not bad, that actually puts it in the משנה. Mishna.
So what does it mean? אלא לאו נכנסים לרשות הבעל ויוצאים מרשות
הבעל לרשות האב. Ella lav nichnasim lirshut habaal ve-yotzin mirshut habaal lirshut
ha'av. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says: ואף על גב דקשיא מתה,
Ve'af al gav d'kashya meisa,
even though in this read the problem is that the explicit difference
between the רישא reisha and the סיפא seifa is that in the
רישא reisha she's alive and in the סיפא seifa she's dead. Okay.
So according to this, that's not clear why we had to introduce
the idea of her being dead in the סיפא seifa of the
משנה. Mishna. Because the question is, עד מפלג בגופה ולאחר מיתה, ad
maflig begufa ule-achar misah, because you could say why is the סיפא
seifa talking about that she died and then how to divide the
estate? ליפלוג בחייה ולפירות. Liflog bechayei ule-peiros. Why not just talk about
that she's alive and who gets the right to the fruit? If
the real difference between the רישא reisha and the סיפא seifa is
when she inherited the property, why did you also introduce the difference
of in the סיפא seifa she's dead and they're dividing the estate,
right? I mean, I know probably people are lost by now but
you'll remember the simple sense of the משנה Mishna says when she's
alive, it says בית שמאי Beis Shammai agrees to בית הלל Beis
Hillel that she has total rights over the property. When she's dead,
what do we do with the estate? So the clear sense of
the משנה Mishna is that the difference between the רישא reisha and
the סיפא seifa is that she's dead. Okay. But now he's saying
I understand that's a problem because according to אביי's Abaye approach it
doesn't matter if she's alive or dead, the issue is when she
got the property, and you're right,
she is alive or dead,
no, whether she's alive or dead, that doesn't matter... well okay, yes.
Anyway, it matters when she got the property. But nevertheless, and yes,
the משנה Mishna in the סיפא seifa could have been talking that
she was alive, and that's a good question, why is the סיפא
seifa talking about that she's dead, let it talk about when she's
alive. But nevertheless, the fact that it uses the phrase property going
in and going out to me indicates that אביי's Abaye read is
the right read of this משנה. Mishna. And then the גמרא Gemara
ends: ותו לא מידי. Ve-tulo midai. And there's nothing left to discuss.
Okay. So of course ותו לא מידי Ve-tulo midai is interesting. Does
that mean that it clearly supports אביי? Abaye? רש"י Rashi says ותו
לא מידי, Ve-tulo midai, if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says where's... רש״י Rashi says ותו לא מידי, v'sulo midi, if you
look at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says, where is רש״י? Rashi?
ותו לא מידי v'sulo midi right near the דבור המתחיל, dibur hamatchil,
he says אין להשיב על כך, ein lahashiv al kach,
there's nothing to respond to this, דודאי דייקא כוותיה, devadai dika kavatei,
וקשיא למיתי. ve kashya l'meiti.
It's not that there's nothing to respond to it and clearly it
goes like אביי. Abaye.
Definitely this phrase supports אביי, Abaye, and the fact that it says
that she's dead is a problem to אביי. Abaye. So it's definitely
that this משנה Mishnah goes both ways. Okay, and תוספות Tosafot has
an interesting question: how do we rule? Because we have now like
four different explanations of this משנה. Mishnah. Although most explanations were about
בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, but how you frame the משנה Mishnah in
terms of בית שמאי Beit Shammai also makes an implication about what
בית הלל's Beit Hillel position is. Let's move on.
No, we're moving on. כנסה הרי היא. Kinsa harei hi.
Now, the end of the משנה Mishnah says after שמעון Shimon marries
her, then she's fully his wife. So the גמרא Gemara says לא,
lo, of course, למאי הלכתא, l'mai hilchasa, for what purpose are you
saying this? אמר רב יוסף ברבי חנינא, Amar Rav Yosef b'Rebbi Chanina,
לומר שמגרשה בגט. lomershe m'garsha b'get. Now after יבום, yibum, there's no
longer any חליצה. chalitzah. Now if they want to get divorced, you
give a גט, get, you don't worry about חליצה chalitzah anymore. ומחזירה,
U'machazirah,
and if after he divorced her he wants to remarry her and
she hasn't married another man in between, then he can remarry her
with קדושין. kiddushin. Okay, so it's now you forget יבום, yibum, normal
wife. The גמרא Gemara says מגרשה בגט פשיטא, m'garsha b'get peshita, obviously
you divorce her with a גט. get. No, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salda
adataich amina, hope it's written לקחה לו לאשה ויבמה, l'kachah lo l'ishah
v'yibemah, אמר רחמנא, amar Rachmana, take her for a wife and do
יבום. yibum. ועדיין יבומי הראשון עליה, V'adayan yivumei harishon aleha, like we
suggested it said before according to רבי אלעזר. Rebbe Elazar. Maybe that's
true even about a cross יבום. yibum. Yes she's the wife, but
she never leaves the status of being the sister-in-law. And therefore if
you want to divorce, it's a גט get and חליצה. chalitzah. So
therefore, where was I? יבומי הראשון עליה בחליצה אין בגט לא, Yivumei
harishon aleha b'chalitzah ein b'get lo,
and therefore maybe only a חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, or also חליצה, chalitzah,
only a חליצה. chalitzah. Anyway, maybe she still has a status of
sister-in-law even after יבום. yibum. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that that's not
true. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that she is considered to be a
normal wife and a divorce would be with a גט. get. ומחזירה
פשיטא? U'machazirah peshita?
So the fact that you can remarry her is obvious? No, it's
not obvious. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salda adataich amina, I might have thought
מצוה דרמיא רחמנא עליה עבדה. mitzvah d'ramya Rachmana aleih avdah. He did
the מצוה mitzvah that the תורה Torah told him he should do,
יבום. yibum. As long as he was in the context of that
initial מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, it overrode the prohibition of brother's
wife. But now that he got divorced and he wants to remarry,
now it's a completely new relationship and she goes back to being
brother's wife. השתא תקומי ליה באיסור
אשת אח. Hashta teikomei lei b'issur eishet ach. Now it's not the
continuation of the act of יבום, yibum, it's a new marriage, so
you go back to being brother's wife. That makes a lot of
sense. קא משמע לן. Kamashmalan. So no, once the act of יבום
yibum is done, her whole status to him changes. So the גמרא
Gemara says ואימא הכי נמי, v'eima hachi nami, okay, those were two
good הוה אמינא'ס, hava amina's, maybe it should be true. No, אמר
קרא ולקחה לו לאשה, amar kra u'lkachah lo l'ishah,
take her for him as a wife. כיון שלקחה הרי היא כאשתו
לכל דבר. Keivan she'lakachah, harei hi k'ishto l'chol davar.
Once the יבום yibum act happened, then it's fully like a wife,
and none of the other status of brother's wife or יבום yibum
or whatever, none of those old statuses are relevant, she's just like
a normal wife for all those implications. Okay.
Yes, ובלבד שתהא כתובתה על
נכסי בעלה הראשון.
u'bilvad she'tehei ktuvatah
al nichsei ba'alah harishon.
The one thing is if now שמעון Shimon dies, when she comes
to collect her כתובה, ktuvah, she collects it from ראובן's Reuven. estate.
Because it makes sense because she initially had it against ראובן, Reuven
שמעון Shimon essentially took it over along with taking over ראובן's Reuven,
estate, but that כתובה ktuvah started with ראובן's Reuven estate so it's
against ראובן's Reuven estate if שמעון Shimon dies. So the גמרא Gemara
says מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, why is it? אשה הקנו לו מן
השמים. Ishah hiknu lo min hashamayim. So
because heaven has given him a wife, which is not exactly so
clear, but maybe it means that the normal purpose of the כתובה...
ktuvah... it's not exactly clear what they mean. I will explain that
to mean that since she is taking over ראובן's Reuven position, so
the כתובה ktuvah also remains vis-a-vis ראובן Reuven and vis-a-vis ראובן's Reuven
estate.
Wait, if you remarry her you're the woman,
that's the obligation for the כתובה? ktuvah? That's another way of saying
it, yes. Anyways the גמרא Gemara says ואי אית לה מן הראשון,
v'is leih min harishon,
but if let's say ראובן Reuven does not have enough property for
her to collect, תקנו לה משני, tiknu lah mishaini, she can still
collect from שמעון's Shimon estate. Why? כדי שלא תהא קלה בעיניו להוציאה,
Kedei shelo tehei kalah be'einav l'hotziah,
because then because even if you didn't need the כתובה ktuvah and
this might be the way Michael was reading it, you don't normally
as we've seen before with the idea of חנא, china, you might
need the כתובה ktuvah to convince a woman to get married. This
woman didn't need to be convinced, unfortunately she didn't have much say
in the matter, you know, it was already being transferred from ראובן.
Reuven Which is obviously a whole problem and you know then we'll
get to that in the next משנה. Mishnah. Anyway, but nevertheless, she
needs the protection of the כתובה. ktuvah. So therefore if they don't
have
enough property in ראובן's Reuven. estate, she can have it against שמעון's
Shimon estate. So תוספות Tosafot says, and why does any of this
matter? Since eventually שמעון Shimon is now in possession of ראובן's Reuven
property, so she's either going to get it from ראובן's Reuven old
property or from שמעון's Shimon property. So תוספות Tosafot works out what
the implications are. All right, let's. All right, let's get on to
next משנה. Mishnah.
Now we turn to, finally, this משנה Mishnah probably should have been
the first משנה Mishnah of the מסכת. Masechet. Okay. מצוה בגדול, Mitzvah
begadol, מצוה בגדול ליבם. Mitzvah begadol leyabem. The מצוה mitzvah is for
the oldest son, oldest brother to do the act of יבום, yibum,
which is saying two things. Number one is the מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum precedes the מצוה mitzvah of חליצה, chalitzah, which should be
pretty obvious. And number two is that the primary obligation devolves on
the older child, on the older brother. לא רצה, Lo ratzah, if
he did not want to do יבום, yibum, מהלכין על כל האחים.
mahlachin al kol ha'achim. You go to the other brothers and see
if you can get any one of them to do יבום, yibum,
presumably then you don't necessarily go by age order. You try to
see if any of the other brothers want to do יבום. yibum.
Of course, notice we're not even asking her what she wants. We'll
get to that, but clearly that's primarily being framed in his perspective.
לא רצו, Lo ratzu, if none of them wanted to do יבום,
yibum, חוזרים אצל גדול. chozrim etzel gadol. You go to the oldest
brother and say to him, עליך מצוה. alecha mitzvah. Look buddy, you
have the responsibility, now you have the responsibility, you gotta take care
of this. או חלוץ או יבם, O chalotz o yabem, either do
חליצה chalitzah or do יבום, yibum, you gotta do one. Okay, so
the basic implications of the משנה Mishnah are clear, right? יבום Yibum
comes before חליצה, chalitzah, we would rather have any brother do יבום
yibum rather than the older brother do חליצה. chalitzah. So basically we
have two priorities: יבום yibum before חליצה, chalitzah, older before younger. When
you have to choose between them, יבום yibum is the more important
one. So if the older says no, you try to get יבום
yibum from another brother. Okay, if יבום yibum isn't on the table,
then the primary obligation is on the older brother and we pressure
him to act in one way or the other.
You'd be turned away?
We're gonna get to that. תולה בקטן עד שיגדיל. Toleh bikatan ad
sheyagdil.
Let's say the older brother says, look, I don't want to do
יבום, yibum, but I have a younger brother, not here just younger,
relatively younger, I have a brother who's ten years old, but I
think when he grows up he'll want to do יבום. yibum. Okay,
so if יבום yibum really comes first, maybe we should wait for
the younger brother to grow up to see? None of the older
brothers wanted to do יבום, yibum, but maybe the younger brother will.
Okay, so okay, או בגדול עד שיבוא ממדינת הים, o hagadol ad
sheyavo mimedinat hayam,
or he says, look, don't pressure me this is the way רש״י
Rashi reads it don't pressure me to do יבום yibum or חליצה,
chalitzah,
the oldest brother, I'm the oldest one who's here, but the really
oldest brother is away in Hawaii. Let's wait for him to come
back and then you'll pressure him to do either יבום yibum or
חליצה. chalitzah. So you don't do either of those cases, okay? או
חרש או שוטה, O cheresh o shoteh, אין שומעין לו. ein shomin
lo.
Or if it's a case about like a חרש cheresh or a
שוטה shoteh that is not able to do יבום, yibum, okay, and
he says, well,
you know, maybe my brother
is deaf-mute, but maybe he'll get
better, or maybe he's got some mental condition, but maybe he'll get
better and then maybe he'll want to do יבום. yibum. In all
those cases, אין שומעין לו, ein shomin lo, you don't listen. אלא
אומרים לו, Ella omin lo, look, we deal with who we have
now and who's in front of us. And right now, nobody who's
in front of us who's able to do יבום yibum wants to
do יבום. yibum. You're the oldest guy in front of us, and
therefore you're the person
that has to do something. So אלא אומרים לו, ella omin lo,
עליך מצוה, alecha mitzvah, you have the מצוה mitzvah buddy, או חלוץ
או יבם, o chalotz o yabem, either do חליצה chalitzah or יבום,
yibum, don't tell me to wait.
That I really will do it once I get back, then we
wait, right?
Presumably, yeah, presumably if you actually got word from an overseas brother
who wanted to do יבום, yibum, then presumably we would.
But we haven't gotten word for that.
But that's a good point, you know, if let's say there was
concrete knowledge about that, like ראובן Reuven was in the process of
dying for a year, right, and שמעון Shimon said, actually, if that
happens and there's still no kid, I want to do יבום, yibum,
and now he's away in מדינת הים. medinat hayam. That would be
an interesting case. But in these cases, we don't know, so we're
saying we're just going to deal with what we've got here and
we're not going to hope maybe something will happen and he'll want
to do יבום yibum etc. Okay, or let's say the קטן katan
says I definitely want to do יבום, yibum, give me a year
till I become בר מצוה, Bar Mitzvah, right? That would be even
a more easier case, right? So that's an interesting question about when
we definitely know the intent. But the emphasis of the משנה Mishnah
seems to be like what more the greater sort of, you know,
pressure is to not delay and to do it right away.
Okay, let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, was taught. ביאת קטן וחליצת
גדול. Bias katan vechalitzas gadol. Now again, קטן katan here does not
mean a minor, okay? קטן Katan means a younger brother. Because to
do the act of יבום yibum with a minor would not work.
All right, we'll get to that later, and you wouldn't allow it
certainly לכתחילה. lechatchilah. So, but the issue is, you've got a younger
brother who says I want to do יבום yibum and you got
the other brother who says I'm ready to do חליצה. chalitzah. Now
the way we read the משנה, Mishnah, what would you say the
answer would be? It should be an obvious answer. Which way would
you go?
Younger brother, older brother.
The older, the younger one wants to do יבום, yibum, the older
one wants to do חליצה. chalitzah.
Go to the oldest brother.
That's when nobody wanted to do יבום. yibum. Right? But if you
actually, it seems like the first thing is let's find somebody to
do יבום. Yibum. If nobody wants to do יבום, Yibum, then we'll
have to figure it out. Okay, that's what it would seem, but
now we're going to have a different read of the משנה. Mishnah.
ביאת קטן וחליצת גדול. Biat katan v'chalitzat gadol. פליגי בה רבי יוחנן
ורבי יהושע בן לוי. Pligi ba Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi.
דבי רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי.
D'vei Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi. חד אמר ביאת קטן עדיפה, Chad amar Biat katan
adifa, we prefer יבום Yibum even of a younger brother, וחד אמר
חליצת גדול עדיפה. v'chad amar Chalitzat gadol adifa. No, the actual thing
that gets more precedence is the older brother, whichever one he wants
to do. So now let's see how to read the משנה. Mishnah.
מן דאמר ביאת קטן עדיפה דמצוה ביבום. Man d'amar Biat katan adifa
d'mitzvah b'yibum.
So the one says you prefer ביאת Biat of the younger brother
because יבום Yibum is the bigger מצוה mitzvah than חליצה. chalitzah. ומן
דאמר חליצת גדול עדיפה, U'man d'amar Chalitzat gadol adifa, and the one
that says that it's the go you go by the older brother,
he doesn't deny that יבום Yibum is the bigger מצוה, mitzvah, he
just says that you gotta focus on who is the person who's
obligated. במקום גדול ביאת קטן לאו כלום הוא. B'makom gadol, biat katan
lav klum hu. If there's an older brother prepared to do something,
he is the primary person obligated. So it might be true that
יבום Yibum is more important, but you don't even start looking at
the other brothers if the older brother is prepared to do one
or the other. He's the guy you focus on. He's our man.
Okay, and therefore you focus on him and do one or the
other, that's your choice. Okay. Sure, we'd rather you do יבום, Yibum,
but we're not even going to look the other brothers if you're
around. So that's the debate. Do you look at the collective of
brothers and say we'd rather get a יבום Yibum out of this
situation, or do you look at the older brother and say as
long as he's doing something, it's his obligation.
We're going to work about the משנה Mishnah in a minute. Okay,
so תנא. tna. Now let's see how this plays out in the
משנה. Mishnah. לא רצה מחזירין על כל האחים. Lo ratza machzirin al
kol ha'achim. If he didn't want to do the way we read
it יבום, Yibum, you try to get one of the other brothers
to do יבום. Yibum. מאי לאו ולא רצה לייבן, Mai lav v'lo
ratza l'yaben,
doesn't it mean that if he did not want to do יבום,
Yibum, אלא לחלוץ, ella lachlot, but he's prepared to do חליצה? chalitzah?
Doesn't matter. וכתני מחזירין אצל אחים, V'katani machzirin etzel achim,
you still try to get a brother to do יבום. Yibum. שמע
מינה ביאת קטן עדיפה. Shma mina biat katan adifa. You see that
יבום Yibum of a younger brother is more important. No, no, no.
That's not the way to read it. לא רצה, Lo ratza, the
way we have to read it is the following: לא רצה לחלוץ
ולא לייבן. Lo ratza lachlot v'lo l'yaben.
The older brother is refusing to do anything. That's when you go
to the younger brothers. Okay, but if he's prepared to do חליצה,
chalitzah, you go with the older brother.
דכבתיה גבי אחים. D'chavatei gabi achim.
So to read that similar then to the other brothers. ולא רצה
v'lo ratza means don't want to do anything, not just don't want
to do יבום. Yibum. So how would you read it? לא רצו
לא לחלוץ ולא לייבן. Lo ratzu lo lachlot v'lo l'yaben. The other
brothers also. They don't want to do anything. They don't want to
do חליצה, chalitzah, they don't want to do יבום. Yibum. So then
if that's true, אמאי חוזרין אצל גדול? amai chozrin etzel gadol?
So you gotta basically compel somebody to do something here against their
will. Meaning as opposed to reading the משנה Mishnah where you go
to the... he says fine, you want me to do חליצה, chalitzah,
I'll do חליצה. chalitzah. Okay. So then you want to go to
the גדול gadol because he's the one primary obligated. But here, nobody
is going along willingly. Okay. So if that's true, why do we
care about going to the primary person who's obligated? Now we're just
going to have to use force and we should just need to
use force and get the thing done, right? Cause nobody is playing
along. So if that's true, לכפייה לכפייה לדידיה תו. lichfiyei lichfiyei l'didi
tu.
Just force the younger brothers. Why now if everybody's refusing and now
we've got to use force, why are we going... I don't understand
it so much either, but the point is now we're just focused
not on who's doing the מצוה mitzvah because everybody's refusing to do
the מצוה. mitzvah. Now we're just focusing on getting the result. So
why do we care about going to the older brother? Anyway the
answer is the obvious answer. כיון דמצוה לדידיה רמיא. Keivan d'mitzvah l'didei
ramya. No, even if we're using force, since the מצוה mitzvah is
primarily on the older brother, לדידיה כפינן. l'didei kaifinan. He's the one
we're gonna force. Yes, we gotta force, we'd rather force the older
one. All right. תנא, Tna, let's try to prove it again. תולה
בקטן עד שיגדיל אין שומעין לו. Toleh b'katan ad sheyagdil ein shomin
lo. If the guy says wait wait, wait for my underaged brother
to grow up, we don't listen to him. Now one minute, why
not? וביאת קטן עדיפה, V'biat katan adifa, if יבום Yibum is always
better even of a younger brother, אמאי אין שומעין לו? amai ein
shomin lo? We should wait for the younger brother to grow up.
אמאי לא שומעין לו? Amai lo shomin lo? נינטר, Nintar, let's wait
for him to grow up. דילמא גדל ומיבם. Dilma gadol u'myaben. Maybe
when he grows up he'll want to do יבום. Yibum. So the
Gemara says I don't understand why that's a question. ולטעמיך, U'l'taimeich, according
to you that you say that the case in the משנה Mishnah
is refusing to do both, ובגדול עד שיבא ממדינת הים שומעין לו?
u'v'gadol ad sheyavo mimedinat hayam shomin lo? How about the case, let's
wait till the older brother comes back from מדינת הים. medinat hayam.
You say we always go by older brother, right? You were asking
me oh we always go by יבום, Yibum, we should wait for
the younger one to grow up. So you say we always go
by older brother. You should wait for the older one to come
back from Hawaii. So אמאי נינטר? amai nintar?
Why should... why do we not wait? נינטר, Nintar, let's wait for
the older one to come back because you say we always prefer
the older one. דילמא אתי וחליץ. Dilma ati v'chalitz. He'll come back
and he'll do whatever he'll do, חליצה chalitzah or יבום. Yibum. But
let's wait for the oldest brother, right? So in both cases you
don't wait for an oldest brother, you don't wait for יבום. Yibum.
So clearly that's a different issue. That's not which one has priority,
that's a question about waiting. אלא כל שהוא עם אשתו לא משהינן.
Ella kol shehu im ishtoh lo mashinan. Bottom line is we don't
wait. No matter what our priorities are, we are not going to
let this thing drag on and we're going to act based on...
and the people that are here right now.
Well, we don't know that. Okay, that was the question you raised,
עגונה aguna case.
All right, איכא דאמרי, ika de'amrei, others say. Let's try to associate
a little bit more. בביאה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דביאת קטן עדיפה.
be'via kuli alma lo pligi debiat katan adifa. No, no, no. If
ייבום yibum is on the table, everybody agrees we prefer ייבום yibum
even by a younger brother. כי פליגי דחליצת קטן. ki pligi de'chalitzas
katan.
The question is, so clearly the ideal is the older brother doing
ייבום. yibum. The next level is younger brother doing ייבום. yibum. Now,
if that's not an option and we have to do חליצה, chalitza,
here is the question. Do we really care who does חליצה? chalitza?
ייבום, yibum, right, there's an implication you're taking over the dead brother's,
the dead brother's name. Maybe there's a bigger idea of the older
brother replacing the dead brother and so on. But חליצה, chalitza, isn't
that all about just getting the act done? So maybe we shouldn't
care who does it. כי פליגי בחליצת קטן. ki pligi b'chalitzas katan.
והכי איתמר, v'hachi itmar, חליצת קטן וחליצת גדול. chalitzas katan v'chalitzas gadol.
If it's between a younger brother doing חליצה chalitza and an older
brother. So, so, פליגי בה רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי. pligi
bah Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. That's a debate. חד אמר
חליצת גדול עדיפה. chad amar chalitzas gadol adifa. No,
even there we'd want the older brother to do the מצוה, mitzvah,
even though it's not going to lead to a marriage and have
broader implications. וחד אמר, v'chad amar, no. כי הדדי נינהו. ke'hadadi ninhu.
Once you're in the חליצה chalitza category, who cares? מאן דאמר חליצת
גדול עדיפה, man de'amar chalitzas gadol adifa, the one says we prefer
the חליצה chalitza of the older brother, דהמצוה בגדול. de'hamitzvah begadol. The
מצוה mitzvah remains in the older brother even in
חליצה. chalitza. ואידך, v'idach, and the other one says no. כי אמרינן
מצוה בגדול, ki amrinan mitzvah begadol, when is that? לענין ייבום, le'inyan
yibum, when it comes to ייבום. yibum. We sort of pointed out,
you know, you're taking the dead brother's name and all of that.
אבל לענין חליצה, aval le'inyan chalitza, but if it's just about creating
severing the relationship, כי הדדי נינהו, ke'hadadi ninhu, they're equivalent. Let's see
how it plays out in the משנה. Mishnah. We'll just read this
one thing. תנן, tnan, לא רצו חוזרין אצל גדול. lo ratzu chozrin
eitzel gadol. If they didn't want to, the younger brothers, you go
back to the older brother. מאי לאו? mai lav? Does that not
mean לא רצו לייבם אלא לחלוץ? lo ratzu leyabem ela lachlotz? The
younger brothers didn't want to do ייבום, yibum, but maybe they did
want to do חליצה. chalitza. So now you've got everybody prepared to
do
חליצה. chalitza. וקתני חוזרין אצל גדול, v'katani chozrin eitzel gadol, you go
to the other one. So you see even if you have everybody
wanting to do חליצה, chalitza, you prefer the older one. ושמע מינה
חליצת גדול עדיפה. ushma mina chalitzas gadol adifa. You see that even
in the world of חליצה chalitza you prefer the older one. לא,
lo, no, that's not what it means. It means לא רצו לא
לחלוץ ולא לייבם. lo ratzu lo lachlotz v'lo leyabem. Everybody is refusing
to do everything. So, and okay, and therefore you go. סלקא דעתך
לגבי גדול, salka deitach legabi gadol, wait a minute, if that's true,
then by the older one, לא רצו לא לחלוץ ולא לייבם, lo
ratzu lo lachlotz v'lo leyabem, everybody's refusing to do everything. In that
case, אלא אמאי חוזרין אצל גדול? ela amai chozrin eitzel gadol? So
then if you've got to force people, why do you have to
force the older one? If we've got to force it anyway, who
cares who we force? לכפייה לכפייה לדידהו, lichfeia lichfeia ledideihu, force the
younger brothers. And again, the גמרא Gemara says very clearly, no. כיון
דמצוה עליה רמיא, keivan demitzvah aleiah ramya, since it's the, and no,
if you're going to force them, maybe he'll agree to do ייבום.
yibum. Right, this side would say if all you're going to get
out of it is a חליצה, chalitza, maybe who, maybe it doesn't
matter. But if ייבום, yibum, now that we're going to force, maybe
it'll result in a ייבום. yibum. So in that case לדידיה כייפינן,
ledidei kaifinan, we're going to force the older one. Okay, we will
end with this for now. Okay.
Oh, you know what? Let's not, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I said
we'll end, but let's just do, I'm sorry, no, no, two more
lines to end the idea. תא שמע, ta shema, just to end
the thing from before. תא שמע, ta shema, תולה בגדול עד שיבא
ממדינת הים אין שומעין לו. tola begadol ad sheyavo mimedinas hayam ein
shomin lo. It says wait for the older brother until he comes
from Hawaii, we don't listen. ואי סלקא דעתך חליצת גדול עדיפה, v'ei
salka deitach chalitzas gadol adifa, if we prefer the חליצה chalitza by
the older brother, אמאי אין שומעין לו? amai ein shomin lo? Why
not? נינטר דילמא אתי וחלץ, nintar dilma ati v'chaletz, let's wait for
him to come back. So the גמרא Gemara says ולטעמיך דקטן עד
שיגדיל אין שומעין לו אמאי? ul'tamaich dekatan ad sheyagdil ein shomin lo
amai? So ask the same question, why don't we wait for the
younger brother, the underage brother to grow up? נינטר דילמא גדל ומייבם,
nintar dilma gadal v'meyabem, let's let him grow up and do ייבום.
yibum. Everybody agrees that's the idea. אלא כל שהיא מצוה לא שהינן.
ela kol shehee mitzvah lo shahinan. We don't do anything to postpone
acting on it. Whatever our series of preferences are and priorities are,
the first thing is get the job done. Okay, now we will
end for today. Okay.
So it's still a מחלוקת machlokes to which you do? Meaning is
it better to do חליצת גדול? chalitzas gadol?
We'll talk about that tomorrow. I mean חליצת גדול, chalitzas gadol, yeah,
that's still a מחלוקת. machlokes. But tomorrow we're going to get even
into the more interesting question of whether nowadays we say חליצה chalitza
comes first or ייבום yibum comes first. Yeah, you had a question.
It's about leaving the woman hanging in an indeterminate status, not being
able to do anything. It's about performing a מצוה mitzvah as quickly
as possible.
Yes, that as well.